Kia ora koutou, my name's Janie and welcome to Case by Case.
This is an open justice podcast brought to you by the New Zealand Herald with thanks to
New Zealand on air.
This week we're looking at a case involving a young offender, a violent home invasion and
we look at the broader questions around how courts balance the nuances of sentencing and
joining me to do all that is Hannah Bartlett from our open justice team.
Hi Hannah.
How are you going?
Hi Jane.
Very well.
Thank you.
through what happened in this case,
and on the night that the offending took place.
I heard about this at a sentencing
that recently took place in the Todunga District Court
for a fairly young man called Cyprus Buchanan.
So he, along with about nine others,
turned up at a Todunga home,
one o'clock in the morning, January 2026.
The group arrived in two separate car loads,
turned up at the house,
broke their way in and basically just stormed around the house,
they're wearing ballot clovers, some were carrying machete's
and just yelling, where's the stuff, took a whole lot of stuff,
threatened people in the house and left.
Okay, so who were the people in the house?
Were they known to them?
By all understanding they weren't known to the offenders,
that it was just a house of people,
there were some young adults and teenagers
and a couple of children aged eight and 12.
The only offender that they actually identified, police actually identified, was Mr Buchanan.
He was wearing a electronically monitored bracelet because he was on parole, release conditions
that required him to wear a bracelet, so he wore the bracelet when he did the offending,
so it wasn't particularly difficult for police to catch up with him and identify that he'd
been involved, given those bracelets tracked people's movements.
So, we don't actually know what Mr Buchanan's specific role was.
We don't know whether he was one of the offenders who was carrying a machete.
We don't know what part of the offending he was involved in.
But broadly speaking, the group goes into the house.
The people inside the house, there were some young adults and teenagers who were still
awake.
It was one o'clock in the morning as I said, but they hid in rooms.
They didn't go into the room where the children were.
of the teenagers went and sort of stood in front of the door and said don't go in. We're not sure
whether that teenager indicated that there were children in the room and that's why they're not
to go in but for whatever reason they didn't go into that room most fully. So they've gone
into this property with machetes and but it's not just to threaten people right there was actual
violence that took place. Yes so one of the offenders confronted one of the young adults
and punched him in the throat, another person was punched in the head 10 times, I believe that was
the 16 year old who then, after being punched in the head all those times, went and stood in front
of the door of the bedroom where the children were. And then with these machetees, they're, you know,
holding the machetees up against the chests and they, one of the, another teenager, you know, hides
under the bed. We don't quite know what the kids were doing in the room, but, you know, they would
would have been hearing what was going on. So the people in the house seem like they were
just trying to de-escalate, get out of the way, let these guys sort of get out of the air.
And they take with them a whole bunch of stuff, including things like Xboxes and phones and
clothing. And one of the kids had some sports medals that they took. So just sort of all
a bit unusual in that these meant particularly high value items, but they went in and took
what they could and left. And this was actually not the first time that cypress Buchanan had
just been in front of the courts, right? The last time I reported on him, he had been
involved in what we sort of refer to as a smash and grab, an aggravated robbery at a Michael
Hill jewelers at Bay Fair in Moreland, Mount Munganooie. And then this offending happens
while he's still wearing his bracelet. Right. And so all of that probably comes into play
when he comes before our judge again. Yes. Yeah. Okay. Tell us what the place,
you know, the place found in his car. Yeah. So that the, as I said, they don't know what his role was,
but they did find a machete underneath his driver's seat, I think it was. They
found an Xbox on the back seat of his car which had a serial number that matched
some packaging that was found at the family home. So there probably wasn't a
lot of dispute that he was involved. No and that's probably indicated by the
fact that he pleaded guilty basically immediately to these charges. So what were
the charges. So he was charged with aggravated burglary. He also faced another
couple of charges that related to what happened after he was arrested so he was
taken back to the Toninga police station. Seems he got quite agitated when he was
being processed by police and he punched a detective constable in the face a couple
of times in the drawer and then when he was later put into a cell he damaged the
south, so just generally being destructive while in custody. So for that, he was charged
with willful damage and for the punch to the deceptive Constable, that's an assault's
police charge.
Okay, so what was started out as one charge turned into three by the end of it, okay.
What did the court hear about the impact on the family? Because at the end of the day
when you strip it back and think at one o'clock in the morning, these people descended on
house with weapons, machete's and bell clavas. So the mother of some of the occupants of the house
provided a victim impact statement sort of on behalf of the family where she talked about
the effects on the various people in the house and it was the sort of impacts that you would perhaps
expect in terms of the emotional trauma and this is their home and now they've got all these associations
with it from this really traumatic event but also things like you know the sports
medals that were taken and now that teenager or young person you know doesn't
want to play the sport in the same way anymore and the the youngest child in
the house the eight-year-old had been really sick through the rest of the
night and the next day just because of the stress of it all hearing what was going
on and the stress of you know waking up to that in the night. So the mother said
some of her older children had now moved out of the house and were reluctant to
even come back and visit. What had been a really happy, secure, normal family home.
She's a solo mum as well so you know she talked about the sort of some of
the challenges of of being a solo mum but that overall she'd always felt
really safe and supported in our community and this had really you know rocked that. But also
there was the officer who was assaulted. So he said that while he's been assaulted on previous
occasions that this was by far the most serious and impactful assault he'd experienced. Okay.
And he said while the assault did not result in any financial loss it has had a psychological impact.
he's now found himself less trusting of others
and more cautious in his interactions with people.
And you were actually present at this hearing, weren't you?
Yes I was.
So let's talk about the sentencing.
What did the Crown think was an appropriate sentence?
So the Crown asked for a starting point of eight and a half years.
So this is taking into account the actual offending.
What happened at the eight and a half years
was for what they were called the lead charge
of aggravated burglary.
And then they wanted an uplift
for the other charges, two charges.
So they asked for an eight and a half years starting point
where defense asked for a starting point of seven years.
Where did the judge land on it?
The judge landed on seven years.
There's a guideline judgment for this
which is a judgment that basically deals
with aggravated robberies.
So it sort of outlines the things that
typically show up in this kind of offending
and what can make it particularly bad.
But she also looked at some other cases
that related particularly to young people.
So she had a look at all these different cases,
the sorts of things that you see across them,
why they were similar and decided that seven years
was an appropriate starting point.
So what was the final sentence? We had the judge decided that seven years was the appropriate
starting point and then there was, we had an uplift of three months for his previous convictions
and uplift for the fact that this happened while he was on e-emporal conditions. But
the worrisome discounts applied in this instance as well. Yes, so we've dealt with the actual
offending what happened and so then when looking at Mr Buchanan and the things about him and his
circumstances that the judge also has to take into account and the big ones for him were his age
and so for his youth he was given a 20% discount so recent changes to the sentence
and yet mean that once you've given a discount for youth you can't get another one if he were
to offend whilst or within that window where ordinarily you would get a youth discount.
he's had his discount, so at least the judge decides it's manifestly unjust, he won't get another
used discount. Gotcha. The other thing about Mr Buchanan is he's unfortunately had a really,
really awful upbringing, things like parental incarceration, parental neglect, exposure to
gangs, violence against him, abuse and state care, just kind of all the things that you
don't want for our for our young people growing up and on top of that he had some
you know specific psychological things going on yeah his own mental health things
like ADHD his ability to sort of emotionally process things yeah so for
his background he was given another 10% discount and then all of this is on top
of the 25% discount for his guilty plea okay so that's where the discount for
The guilty plea comes in.
So we get to a total of 55% discounts,
which is as high as part of the sentencing act.
Now there's actually a 40% cap on discounts,
but parliament has given judges discretion
to be able to assess whether having that cap
in individual circumstances might be manifestly unjust,
bearing in mind the circumstances of a case.
And in this case, the judge decided
that it would be manifest the unjust.
So that resulted in an end sentence of three years
and nine months imprisonment.
Okay, and he's soothing that right now.
Yes, he also had what's called a first strike warning.
So that under three strikes legislation,
it's basically each time someone commits
a qualifying offense, they'll be given a warning.
And the warning sort of get more serious
in terms of what the implications will be
and if they're brought back to court again.
And so that's legislation that's what was in
and then was out and it's been brought back in.
It's very complicated.
We are going to be talking a lot more about
sentencing, about discounts and uplifts and so on.
It's contentious stuff for the public a lot of the time,
so we're going to dig into it
and see if we can make some sense of it after the break.
Hey, John, I'm Ben and Megan here.
You can catch our podcast right now.
On today's show, you help us work
been through the seven stages of grief after the while.
Yeah, I'm on my hands and knees in the middle of the road
at 4.30 in the morning.
Find out why.
And I accidentally gave a man a fix
for my washing machine the worst customer satisfaction
rating possible.
So we've all had a great day.
Catch your podcast right now on iHeartRadio.
You're with Case by Case, an open justice podcast brought
to you by the New Zealand Herald,
with thanks to New Zealand on ear.
My name's Jane Ye, and we're about to dive into sentencing.
We're talking to Hannah Bartlett from the open justice team
here at the Herald, sentencing often very contentious
with the public, people have their records,
and particularly when it comes to discounts,
because so discounts, probably a better way
to think about discounts is actually the word adjustments.
So when we're looking at a sentencing,
the first thing to understand is that it happens in two parts.
So the first part looks at what the person did,
the second part looks at who the person is.
Okay. And first of all, it's important to note that sentencing is governed by a piece
of legislation called the Sentencing Act. That's put there by Parliament, judges
enact it, and so they have to follow the purposes and principles of the Sentencing Act, which
are, you know, a varied, but they include things like denunciation, deterrence,
holding the person accountable, protecting the community, assisting in the offenders
is rehabilitation and reintegration.
So already, even when you're just looking at that,
there's some competing things that they have to balance.
So the first part of the sentencing
looks at what the person did, the offending itself.
And that's where we get this term, the starting point.
To reach that starting point, the judge
looks at some of the characteristics of the offending.
And we often hear the term aggravating factors.
So these are the things that make the offending
particularly bad.
The judge will look at other similar cases
that involve similar kinds of offending
because one of the important things about our sentencing act
is that it does require that sentences be fair.
So once we've dealt with the offending itself,
we have the starting point,
then the attention turns to the offender themselves,
their personal circumstances.
And this is where we get into the territory of discounts,
but also sometimes the adjustments go up in this way
because if, for example, someone has previous convictions,
if their offending happened while the person was on bail
or particularly on electronic monitoring bail,
if they have previous convictions,
then the sentence will sometimes go up.
The things that will bring the sentence down,
their personal circumstances,
that might help for court understand
why their offending has happened.
So the really common ones are that they're young,
so a youth discount usually can be applied
to someone who's under the age of 25 roughly,
and that's based on sort of what we understand
about neuroscience, that the brain is still developing,
that there's a higher likelihood of impulsivity,
lack of consequential thinking and all of those things that can show up when someone is
offending when they're younger. It also recognises that younger people are more likely to be able
to be rehabilitated. The other ones are you know they've never been in trouble before,
they have no previous convictions, they come from a really rough background and again this
recognises what we know about neurodevelopment that you know your pathways are being formed
right from the time you're born and if you've been exposed to violence, exposed to drugs,
you've come from a background where there's been neglect, you've come from a background where
offending has been normalised. You've been sent on a path that's not your choosing and so the courts
recognise that they probably do need to be at least an allowance made for the fact that this person
has ended up where they are versus someone who's come from a perfectly normal childhood,
has had every opportunity, perhaps has, you know, a really secure financial
position and still chooses to go and behave in an anti-social way. It can be
very difficult, I'm sure, for victims of these crimes to see people getting discounts, right?
So do they get a say in all of this? They do. And so one of the things that
they have to balance that against is the impact on the victim and that is also
in there in the sentencing act. The way that the court hears about that is often
through what's called a victim impact statement and this is where victims are
really given a say in the actual court process so they provide a statement to
the court ahead of sentencing. The judge reads it, the person can choose to read
it out to themselves or have it read by a prosecutor or the police officer in
charge of the case and that tells the judge what the impact has been on them. So it might
be things like the counselling that's still being needed, ongoing physical rehabilitation
if it's been a violent act, the mental health impacts, the impacts on other relationships,
the loss of trust and other people, and an ability to work the stress of the actual court
process and that brings us back to another discount that I think people must understand
and that's the guilty plea discount. So the earlier that you plead guilty, the bigger the
discount, so it starts at 25% if you plead guilty basically at the earliest opportunity
and then it drops away as you get further through the court process. That recognises
A, the cost of taking things to trial, it recognises the impact on the victim,
the amount of court time that's sucked up, getting prepared for a trial and all of those things.
And it provides an incentive for people to put up their hand and not just go,
oh, well, we'll just take it to trial and see what happens.
I've got nothing to lose.
Yeah, exactly right.
Ultimately, what is sentencing trying to achieve?
And I think this is the key question.
And I know it's a tricky one to answer because it's a balancing act.
But to me, it's the key question because when we are raising concerns about giving people
discounts for things, oftentimes we're thinking purely punitively.
But when you stop and think, okay, what is the purpose of sentencing?
What are we trying to achieve with our justice system?
There are other things that play. Can you talk a little to that?
you know, you have the denunciation, which is basically us saying this isn't behaviour
that we as a community tolerate.
The deterrence is, you know, you sort of, you're hoping that all other people will see this and
go, oh no, I don't want to, I don't want to be set to prison for that amount of time,
so I won't, I won't behave in that way.
But then we do have, as part of our sentence, saying this idea that it should assist in
a defendant's rehabilitation, because ultimately we aren't keeping people in prison forever
and then just locking them in and throwing away the key. They do have to be released. And so
finding a way to balance the sentence that is going to somehow assist in that rehabilitation
not end up with people who are just institutionalised. One of the concerned people judges have about
sending particularly young people to prison is that you're sending a young person into an
environment where they're going to be mixing with older people who are more set in their criminal
ways and is that really what we want our young people doing is is there another way and so
all of that has to be taken into account and that's where with young people in particular
judges are more inclined to impose non-custodial sentences. So it means not necessarily prison.
not necessarily present. So we do have some other sentences that are available to judges
if a term in imprisonment is of two years or less. So the one people probably most familiar with
is home detention. That's where you basically just got to stay at home 24-7 and it's to a specific
address. Then we have community detention that's also an electronically monitored sentence like
home detention where someone's wearing a bracelet at judges less keen on that one because sometimes
referred to as the punishment to sleep in your own bed at night as a normally an overnight curfew
and so you can go out during the day but then you're at home overnight. Then there's things
like community work with you know going out putting out rubbish that kind of thing that
I'm sure there's a lot more options or community work sentences but that's the general idea
is, you know, giving back to the community in some way, supervision, and then there are
fines.
Yeah, right.
So there's a real mixture of the area of options, and also I guess you sometimes hear
people comparing sentences of what can look like the same criminal activity.
One person can rob a bank and end up with this sentence, and someone else can do a very
similar crime and end up with a much harsher sentence, and all the things that we've discussed
today are the reasons why these sentences can differ.
Yes, and there's huge variables in terms of the actual offending,
what happened, but then as we've talked about massive differences
and who these people are and what circumstances are particular
to them, their age, their background, all the rest of it,
and sort of the circumstances around their offending.
And judges are given a whole lot of information about that.
Most of it, we don't see, you might not know,
there's psychological reports, there's background reports,
there's support leaders from the community,
there's leaders of remorse,
there's all these things that go into it.
And again, so much information about what actually happened
and the events and the circumstances of it.
And that part of the process is usually,
there's a bit more transparency,
but all that other stuff,
there's a lot of private information in there
that, you know, members of the public aren't necessarily entitled to, but the judges taking
into account.
So we just have to trust that they know what they're doing and that they're doing the best
thing for all of us.
Sure.
And the judges balancing that thing of keeping the community safe and holding this person
to account and hopefully imposing a sentence that somehow meets both of those things and
helps this person start to learn from their mistakes to become rehabilitated and move
on in a positive way.
Yeah, so future-proofing the community safety as well,
not just keeping them safe while someone's incarcerated,
but thinking about when their person comes out,
what their prospects are going to be like.
Yes. Hey, thank you so very much, Hannah.
It was lovely to chat with you again.
Really appreciate your time.
That's being case by case.
An Open Justice podcast brought to you by the New Zealand Herald
with thanks to New Zealand on air.